Niklas Fahl







I am an iOS developer with 6+ years of experience developing apps and a passion for designing and implementing beautiful and pixel-perfect user interfaces. I am looking to apply my skills to exciting new challenges as well as to strengthen and broaden my skills as an iOS developer.

WORK EXPERIENCE

iOS Software Developer

June 2014 - Present

Center for Advanced Public Safety, Tuscaloosa, AL

- Design and develop iOS applications in an agile small team environment such as ALGO Traffic,
 UA Safety, CAPS Leave, and TCSO
- Responsible for designing clean user interfaces that enhance the user experience
- Maintain existing iOS applications and develop new feature in collaboration with clients
- Collaborate with back-end developers on the design of RESTful JSON API's to facilitate the consumption of these API's in iOS applications
- Collaborate with web and Android developers to ensure parity of user experience and features across all platforms
- Responsible for unit testing as well as external testing via TestFlight deployments
- Lead meetings with clients including presentations and demos at each milestone of the projects
- Mentored, trained, and managed several student developers

Undergraduate Research Assistant

March 2013 - May 2014

Center for Advanced Public Safety, Tuscaloosa, AL

- Worked as part of the mobile team to develop iOS applications
- Responsible for user interface design and user experience

SKILLS

Swift

Swift Package Manager, CocoaPods

UIKit, SwiftUI

Git, Git flow

German (Native)

Xcode

Figma, Sketch

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

PROJECTS

CAPS Leave October 2019 - Present

Developed for the Center for Advanced Public Safety

This app lets users add work-leave events to their outlook calendar directly through the app using predefined leave types such as annual leave and sick leave. The app also features report functionality that lets the users get an overview of the leaves taken during a certain period of time. The user is also able to get an overview of other people's leave events that are coming up today or in the future if they have been invited to the event.

Language: Swift

Tools and Technology: Figma, Microsoft Auth Library, UlKit, Storyboard, Git

Notable Features:

- Implemented date conversion and date range calculations to display leave events properly depending on what time zone the user is in in relation to the time zone their job is located in
- Implemented configurable work schedule to allow for omission of lunch breaks and overall more accurate leave time calculations

App Store: bit.ly/CAPSLeaveApp

UA Safety

November 2018 - Present

Developed for the University of Alabama Office of Emergency Management

This app provides users with live safety updates including push notifications for the University of Alabama campus community such as university alerts and weather alerts. The app also features a listing of all buildings on campus and their safety features such as storm shelters and defibrillators as well as safety guidelines for events such as severe weather.

Language: Swift

Tools and Technology: Sketch, UlKit, Firebase SDK, Swift Package Manager, MapKit, CoreLocation,

RESTful JSON API, Git

Notable Features:
• Push notifications, analytics, and crash reporting (Firebase)

Features a live radio stream of the university's info radio station

Mapping of, and proximity to, campus buildings

Integrates with a RESTful JSON API to display weather alerts, campus

alerts, campus buildings, and safety guidelines

App Store: bit.ly/UASafetyApp

PROJECTS

ALGO Traffic April 2018 - Present

Developed for the Alabama Department of Transportation

This app provides users with live traffic updates such as accidents, road work, and other road hazards for state funded roads (i.e. Interstates, State Routes, US Routes) in Alabama. The app also features live camera feeds that lets the user monitor traffic in certain areas they may be traveling. When traveling the user can engage driving mode, which provides traffic updates of what's ahead while driving.

Language: Swift

Tools and Technology: Sketch, UlKit with XIB's, Google Maps SDK, Firebase SDK, GeoJSON, Core

Location, AVFoundation, CocoaPods, RESTful JSON API, Git

Notable Features:

• Display weather alerts and traffic events from a RESTful JSON API on the map

 Detect when the user is leaving Alabama to provide information on where to get traffic updates in surrounding states

• Driving Mode matches the user with traffic events that are coming up on their route and announces them when they are a specific distance from any given event for a hands free experience

Live traffic camera feeds

Analytics and crash reporting (Firebase)

App Store: bit.ly/ALGOTrafficApp

TCSO November 2017 - Present

Developed for the Tuscaloosa County Sheriff's Office

This app gives users an overview of recent arrests, most wanted, people with warrants, crime reports, and sex offenders in Tuscaloosa County. The app also provides information about services Tuscaloosa County Sheriff's Office provides and lets users submit tips anonymously directly to the Tuscaloosa County Sheriff's Office.

Language: Swift

Tools and Technology: Sketch, UIKit with XIB's, OneSignal SDK, Firebase SDK, CocoaPods,

RESTful JSON API, Git

Notable Features:

• Integrate with a RESTful JSON API to display recent arrests, crime

reports, and sex offender listings as well as office locations and tornado

shelters

Anonymous tip feature lets users send crime related tips directly to the

Tuscaloosa County Sheriff's Office

Analytics and crash reporting (Firebase)

App Store: bit.ly/TCSOApp